<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-08-08T06:30:14+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quasi-Normal Coupled Mode Theory</title><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/QuasiNormalModeCouplingTheory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quasi-Normal Coupled Mode Theory"/><published>2022-10-23T16:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-10-23T16:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/QuasiNormalModeCouplingTheory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/QuasiNormalModeCouplingTheory/"><![CDATA[<p>The coupled mode theory (CMT) has not been treated systematically in lossy and irreciprocal scattering problem and is normally used in an intuitive manner. As a result, we need to formalize the so called quasi-normal coupled mode theory (QCMT) to be consistent with the scattering in low-Q, dispersive and irreciprocal scenario.</p> <p>This post refers the following two papers:</p> <ul> <li><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.08650">Quasi-normal Coupled Mode Theory</a></li> <li><a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/lpor.201700113">Light Interaction with Photonic and Plasmonic Resonances</a></li> </ul> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/posts_img/scattering_problem.jpg" width="450" height="200"/> <figcaption> A schematic figure of a general scattering problem.</figcaption> </center> </figure> <p>In a general scattering problem, the discrepance from a Hermitian problem could stem from</p> <ul> <li>Non-Hermitian Operator: Lossy; Dispersivel irreciprocal</li> <li>Non-Hermitian Boundary Conditions: Open Boundary</li> </ul> <p>The general scattering prblem could be described by the following dynamic equation:</p> \[\underbrace{\left(\begin{array}{cc} &amp;\nabla \cdot \\ \nabla \cdot &amp; \end{array}\right)}_{\Theta} \underbrace{\left(\begin{array}{c} \boldsymbol{Q} \\ \boldsymbol{P} \end{array}\right)}_\psi-\dfrac{\partial}{\partial t} \left(\underbrace{\left(\begin{array}{cc} 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; -1 \end{array}\right)+\Delta B}_B\right)\left(\begin{array}{c} \boldsymbol{Q} \\ \boldsymbol{P} \end{array}\right)=-\underbrace{\left(\begin{array}{c} \boldsymbol{J}_q \\ -\boldsymbol{J}_p \end{array}\right)}_{\xi}\] <p>The eigenmodes of such a problem, in general, form a complete orthonormal basis to describe fields in the scatter in the following manner:</p> \[\begin{aligned} \Theta \psi_{\mathrm{R}, m} &amp;=\mathrm{i} \widetilde{\omega}_m B\left(\widetilde{\omega}_m\right) \psi_{\mathrm{R}, m} \\ \Theta \psi_{\mathrm{L}, n} &amp;=\mathrm{i} \widetilde{\omega}_n B^T\left(\widetilde{\omega}_n\right) \psi_{\mathrm{L}, n}\\ \int_V \psi_{\mathrm{L}, n}^T B \psi_{\mathrm{R}, n}&amp;=1. \end{aligned}\] <p>With the above, the description of the coupled mode theory could extend to broader cases. The validity of conventional CMT could be checked in the rigorous derivations as well. The exact QCMT theory allows us to uniquely answer this question. The QCMT theory reduces to conventional CMT when the following conditions hold:</p> <ol> <li>The Born-scattering background term is small.</li> <li>The coupling strengths must be approximately frequency-independent over the bandwidth of interest.</li> </ol> <p>The later is a more precise statement of the well-understood requirement that CMT requires high-quality-factor, well-separated resonances.</p> <p>Please check the attached <a href="/assets/img/posts_img/QCMT.pptx">slides</a> for details.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="math"/><category term="linear_algebra"/><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rigorous coupled mode theory for general scattering problem]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Art of Linear Algebra</title><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Art_of_linear_algebra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Art of Linear Algebra"/><published>2022-08-11T11:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-11T11:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Art_of_linear_algebra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Art_of_linear_algebra/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="math"/><category term="linear_algebra"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Graphic Note on Linear Algebra by `kenjihiranabe`]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Matrix World</title><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Matrix_World/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Matrix World"/><published>2022-08-11T10:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-11T10:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Matrix_World</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Matrix_World/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="math"/><category term="linear_algebra"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Picture of All Matrices by `kenjihiranabe`]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Topology of a pair of pants: The Hole Truth</title><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Topological_Isomorphism_of_pants/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Topology of a pair of pants: The Hole Truth"/><published>2022-08-09T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-09T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Topological_Isomorphism_of_pants</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Topological_Isomorphism_of_pants/"><![CDATA[<p>Finished a day’s work, walking along HillHouse Ave with my colleague, I am touched by the soft breeze in summer sunset. Starting with a random question by me: “How many holes are there in a pair of pants?”, we are divided into two groups with answers 2 and 3, respectively. The argument from me that a pair of pants have three holes is given by: Imagine blow your a pair of pants into a ballon, and the hole on your waist and two holes for two legs will be three punched holes on that \(S^2\) sphere surface.</p> <figure> <center> <img src="/assets/img/posts_img/Sphere_with_three_holes.jpg" width="200" height="200"/> <figcaption> A S^2 sphere with three "holes" on the surface.</figcaption> </center> </figure> <p>Another argument states a pair of pants are topologically equivalent to a Thong underwear, which is indeed a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Genus_%28mathematics%29">genus-2 surface</a>!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <center> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/posts_img/Thong_underwear.png" width="auto" height="200" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A Thong Underwear </div> </center> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <center> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/posts_img/Genus-2%20surface.jpg" width="auto" height="200" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A Genus-2 Surface </div> </center> </div> </div> <p>After some thoughts, the shortcut to bridge the gap between these two arguments is expanding one of the holes in \(S^2\) to infinity and it ends up with a Thong underwear shape geometry. This intriguing thought leads me to dig a bit deeper in the definition of the holes.</p> <p>In everyday language, we use “hole” in a variety of nonequivalent ways. One is as a cavity, like a pit in the ground. Another is as an opening or aperture in an object, like a tunnel through a mountain or the punches in three-ring binder paper. Yet another is as a completely enclosed space, such as an air pocket in Swiss cheese. A topologist would say that all but the first example are holes. What are holes?</p> <blockquote> <p>A hole in a mathematical object is a topological structure which prevents the object from being continuously shrunk to a point.</p> </blockquote> <p>When dealing with topological spaces, a disconnectivity is interpreted as a hole in the space. Examples of holes are things like the “donut hole” in the center of the torus, a domain removed from a plane, and the portion missing from Euclidean space after cutting a knot out from it.</p> <h4 id="donut-like-hole">Donut-like hole</h4> <p>The Euler number, V – E + F describes the different holes. Another way of counting this type of holes was by seeing how many times the object could be cut without producing two pieces. For a surface with boundary, such as a straw with its two boundary circles, each cut must begin and end on a boundary. So, according to Riemann, because a straw can be cut only once — from end to end — it has exactly one hole. If the surface does not have a boundary, like a torus, the first cut must begin and end at the same point. A hollow torus can be cut twice — once around the tube and then along the resulting cylinder — so by this definition, it has two holes.</p> <h4 id="generalization">Generalization</h4> <p>The number of these holes — one for each dimension — became known as the Betti numbers of the object in honor of Enrico Betti.</p> <p>The modern definition of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homology_(mathematics)">homology</a> is quite involved, but it is roughly a means of associating to each shape a certain mathematical object. From this object we can extract simpler information about the shape, like its Betti numbers or its Euler number. For instance, we can say with mathematical certainty that a straw, a T-shirt and a pair of pants are all topologically different objects because their homology groups are different. In particular, they have a different number of holes.</p> <p>So, finally, how do topologists count holes? Using the Betti numbers. The zeroth Betti number, b0, is sort of a special case. It simply counts the number of objects. So for a single connected shape, \(b_0\) = 1. As we just saw, the first Betti number, \(b_1\), is the number of circular holes in a shape — like the circle around the cylindrical straw, the three holes in binder paper and the two circular directions of the torus. And Poincaré showed us how to compute homology, and thus the associated Betti numbers, in higher dimensions as well: The second Betti number, \(b_2\), is the number of cavities — like those inside a sphere, a torus and Swiss cheese. More generally, \(b_n\) counts the number of n-dimensional holes.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/posts_img/Topology-Straw-bkg.jpg" alt="drawing" width="750"/></p> <p>A related <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/topology-101-how-mathematicians-study-holes-20210126/">nice article</a> from QuantaMagzine also discuss this and a <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/2132091/n-dimensional-holes">stackexchange discuss</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="math"/><category term="thoughts"/><category term="lunchchat"/><category term="random"/><category term="math"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It starts with a question&#58; how many holes do a pair of pants have?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to build a personal website</title><link href="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Building_personal_website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to build a personal website"/><published>2022-08-08T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Building_personal_website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yiqiwangphysics.github.io/blog/2022/Building_personal_website/"><![CDATA[<p>I decided to build my personal website a week ago and did some research on different options for people who do not have SWE expertise with lots of HTML coding experience. Here are a few options I found be approachable:</p> <h4 id="website-options">Website Options</h4> <ul> <li>Google site: Free but less customizable.</li> <li>Commercial: easy graphical interface, lots of useful modules and templates, but not free if you want to connect to your own domain, like Wix, or WordPress.</li> <li>GitHub Page: Free and plenty of open source templates, slightly challenging as you need some basic HTML knowledge.</li> </ul> <p>Feel it would be fun to learn something new and more comfortable building new architecture from the base, as you may notice on the website footer, I chose the last.</p> <h4 id="more-steps">More Steps</h4> <p>Starting with an existing template is always a shortcut. <a href="https://github.com/topics/personal-website">Github topics</a> provide several clean and concise open-source templates. And you could also find templates from others’ GitHub page if they make theirs public. They also come with detailed README files or articles or even videos to guide you through how to use the template. Follow the instructions, and you are all set!</p> <h4 id="tips">Tips</h4> <p>Here I will share some issues I have encountered and some tools/websites I find to be useful:</p> <ul> <li>To compile and run the website locally, you have to configure your packages correctly. For instance, this template requires installed Ruby and Bundler. For macOS users, you should check your installed Ruby by <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ruby -v</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">which ruby</code> in your terminal. Please not use the system Ruby for <a href="https://www.freecodecamp.org/news/do-not-use-mac-system-ruby-do-this-instead/">the following reasons</a>. A version manager helps if you’re juggling multiple projects and can’t update all at once. For a guide that compares version managers and shows the best way to install Ruby, please check <a href="https://mac.install.guide/ruby/index.html">this article</a>. Ah Ha, now you are ready to compile your website locally and make changes in files and see its effect in no time! :smiley:</li> <li>Like your website, <a href="https://atom.io">Atom</a> is a good app to use to manage a project. You could keep tracking all changes you staged and all changes you commit to master before you deploy your changes in GitHub.</li> <li>Markdown and Html are still needed to customize your website more than the template. Here are some useful references if you are new to <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/html/html_styles.asp">Markdown</a> or <a href="https://www.w3schools.com/html/html_styles.asp">HTML</a> or <a href="https://gist.github.com/rxaviers/7360908">Markdown Emoji</a>.</li> <li>For HTML, there are <a href="https://www.html.am/reference/html-special-characters.cfm">special characters</a> reserved in HTML. That is because these are the characters that make up the HTML language. If you use one of these characters in an article, the browser will try to interpret it as HTML. Therefore, you should use the entity name or entity number when you want to output any of these reserved characters.</li> </ul> <h4 id="domain">Domain</h4> <p>You could connect your Github page to your personal domain. The domain I registered is from the <a href="https://domains.google/?gclid=Cj0KCQjwrs2XBhDjARIsAHVymmStoNKEfhFv-t_uL7XyhHznQ58uVs-YupQMi4Gu5szADC-Fcemzb1caAv65EALw_wcB&amp;gclsrc=aw.ds">Google domain</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="skill"/><category term="tool"/><category term="random"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Guide to build personal website with no SWE experience]]></summary></entry></feed>